Guide to the Jack G. Shaheen Papers TAM.535
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II. Media Research and Advocacy Files, 1968-2011; 4.5 Linear Feet in five record cartons and two oversize folders
  - Subseries II.B. Advocacy and Media Accountability Files, 1976-2010; 2 Linear Feet in three record cartons and one oversize folder
    This subseries documents Shaheen's advocacy work to contest negative stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims in American popular culture and media, and to recommend ways to combat them. This subseries contains materials related to Shaheen's independent advocacy work and that conducted with the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC), and dates from 1976 to 2010. Materials include ADC publications, correspondence between Shaheen and ADC members, material from ADC annual conventions, and research conducted by Shaheen for the ADC. The latter includes Shaheen's reports, notes, and correspondence on the ADC Research Institute Television Cartoon Monitoring Project (1993-1994). This subseries also includes correspondence between Shaheen and major television networks regarding negative depictions of Arabs and Muslims in their series and movies, and with organizations and individuals regarding his advocacy work. Also included are materials from workshops on Arab stereotypes, including questionnaires and notes.
    - American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee -- General files, 1979-2010 (Box 14, Folder 30-47, Box 15, Folder 1-6)
    - American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee -- ADC Research Institute Television Cartoon Monitoring Project files, 1989-1995 (Box 15, Folder 7-13, Box 66, Folder 8)
    - American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee -- Television monitoring files, 1976-2003 (Box 15, Folder 14-23)
    - Correspondence, 1976-2008 (Box 15, Folder 24-34, Box 16, Folder 1-9)
    - Workshop files, 1990-2008 (Box 16, Folder 10-11)
- Series III. Consulting Files, 1983-2005; 0.75 Linear Feet in two record cartons and one oversize folder
  This series is arranged in two subseries: Subseries III.A. Entertainment Production Files and Subseries III.B. Legal Case Files. Neither have been further arranged beyond the subseries level.
  This series documents Shaheen's work as a consultant and expert on Arab stereotypes in legal cases and in the film and television industries. This series dates between 1983 and 2005 and includes correspondence, research materials, reports compiled for legal cases, and scripts. This series contains files on Shaheen's work on the films Three Kings (1999) and Syriana (2005).
  - Subseries III.A. Entertainment Production Files, 1983-2005; 0.25 Linear Feet in one record carton
    This subseries contains Shaheen's files on his consulting work in the entertainment industry and dates from 1983 to 2005. The bulk of the subseries documents Shaheen's work on the films Three Kings (1999) and Syriana (2005), and includes scripts, Shaheen's notes on the scripts, correspondence, and contracts. Correspondents include James C. G. Conniff, Patricia Laucella, Charles Roven, and Douglas Segal. Other materials include correspondence between Shaheen and media networks regarding his consulting work on television movies from the early 1980s to the early 2000s.
    - Entertainment production files, 1983-2005 (Box 16, Folder 12-21)
  - Subseries III.B. Legal Case Files, 1986-1999; 0.5 Linear Feet in one record carton and one oversize folder
    This subseries documents Shaheen's work as an expert witness on Arab stereotypes and cultures in legal cases and dates from 1986 to 1999. Materials include reports written by Shaheen, court documents, correspondence between Shaheen and law firms, and his notes for his expert witness testimony.
    - Legal case files, 1986-1999 (Box 16, Folder 22-29, Box 17, Folder 1-8, Box 65, Folder 15)
- Series IV. Subject Files, 1962-2011; 4.5 Linear Feet in five record cartons and four oversize folders; 3 MiniDV
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic or format of material.
  This series contains subject files compiled by Shaheen on general issues related to Arab-Americans, the media, and communications. The series dates from 1962 to 2011, and includes clippings, dissertations, reports, correspondence, and notes. Shaheen's work to create the Jack G. and Bernice M. Shaheen Endowed Media Scholarship to support Arab-American students in the field of communications is documented in this series, with reports written by Shaheen on who would be supported by the scholarship. This series contains files created by Shaheen pertaining to the hijacking of the Achille Lauro, the murder of Alex Odeh, and general topics related to Arabs and Muslims, the Middle East, discrimination, and stereotypes. Dissertations related to Shaheen's areas of study are included in this series as are materials from conferences which he attended. Other material in this series includes Shaheen's curricula vitae from the 1990s, notes from members of his family and to himself, administrative material pertaining to his time at Southern Illinois University at Edwardsville, and video recordings of interviews with three people on an unspecified topic.
  - Alex Odeh and Achille Lauro files, 1985-2005 (Box 17, Folder 9-10)
  - Arab and Muslim general files, 1967-2011 (Box 17, Folder 11-31, Box 18, Folder 1-12, Box 24, Cd 3-5, Box 66, Folder 3, Folder 7, Folder 11)
  - Biographical materials, 1967-1994, undated (Box 18, Folder 13-18)
  - Conference files, 1993-2001 (Box 18, Folder 19-20)
  - Discrimination files, 1991-2007 (Box 18, Folder 21-24)
  - Dissertations, 1962-2003 (Box 18, Folder 25-33, Box 19, Folder 1-19, Box 20, Folder 1-2)
  - Interviews, 2010 (Box 24, Video 11-13)
  - Jack G. and Bernice M. Shaheen Endowed Media Scholarship files, 2006-2011 (Box 20, Folder 3-4)
  - Middle East general files, 1975-1999 (Box 20, Folder 5-15)
  - Scholarly articles and conference presentations, 1968-2010 (Box 20, Folder 16-29)
  - Stereotypes general files, 1975-2005 (Box 20, Folder 30-35, Box 21, Folder 1-8, Box 65, Folder 16)
- Series V. Study Artifacts and Ephemera, 1943-2012; 8 Linear Feet in three record cartons, two manuscript boxes, one oversize flat box, and one map case folder
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by format type. A box level inventory is available in the repository for items in boxes 60, 61, and 62.
  This series contains material collected by Shaheen that depicts stereotypical images of Arabs and Muslims. Material in this series dates from 1943 to 2012 and includes comic books, games (board games, card games, and video games), movie posters and stills, advertisements, bumper stickers, tobacco tins, Halloween masks, puppets, t-shirts, cigarette lighters, food containers, mugs, Christmas ornaments, dolls, sheet music, sound recordings on disc, toys and stickers, and a placemat. Disney's Aladdin and stereotypical images of Arabs from the 1970s and 1980s are well documented in these materials. The bulk of this series consists of Shaheen's comic book collection, which includes issues of Batman, The Living Mummy, Uncle Scrooge, Wolverine, X-Men, Sinbad, Superman, The Punisher, and 1001 Arabian Nights: The Adventures of Sinbad. Also included are issues of The 99, a comic book featuring a cast of all-Islamic superheroes.
  - Advertisements, 1980-1997, undated (Box 21, Folder 9, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS003, Folder 4, Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Bumper stickers, 1975-1989, undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1964-2010 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Comic books, 1943-2012 (Box 21, Folder 12-28, Box 22, Folder 1-24, Box 23, Folder 1-12, Box 72, Folder 1-6)
  - Games, 1983-1990 (Box 23, Folder 13-15, Box 60, Box 67)
  - Images of Arabs in periodicals and film and television stills, 1980-1999 (Box 23, Folder 16-20, Box 64, Folder 1, Box 72, Folder 7-9)
  - Posters, 1958-2003 (Box 23, Folder 21, Flat-file-folder 8, Box 64, Folder 2-9, Box 72, Folder 10, Flat-file-folder 4, Flat-file-folder 5)
  - Sheet music, Undated (Box 23, Folder 22)
  - T-shirts, masks, toys, and other ephemera, 1980-2010 (Box 23, Folder 23, Box 60, Box 61, Box 62, Box 64, Folder 10)
- Series VI. Video Recordings and Films, 1980-2012, undated; 40 Linear Feet in 35 record cartons, one manuscript box, and three oversize flat boxes; 224 DVDs; 1 Blue-ray; 1 CD-ROM; 609 VHS; 20 film reels; 1 2_Inch_Videoreel
  This series has not been further arranged beyond the series level. A box-level inventory is available in the repository.
  This series contains commercial video recordings and films collected by Shaheen, all of which contain depictions of Arabs and Muslims. The series contains VHS cassettes, DVDs, and 16 mm film reels of movies (feature length and shorts), cartoons, music videos, television series, and a television commercial. The titles span from She (1911) to Disney: Treasure Buddies (2012) and include American and foreign films, Disney and Warner Brothers cartoons, pro-wrestling videos, and music videos. The feature films cover almost every genre of film, with romance, comedies, action/adventure, sci-fi, horror, and children/family being the best represented. The most prominent stereotypes in this series are depictions of Arabs as sheikhs and terrorists, with movies featuring tales of Sinbad, Aladdin, and mummies also well represented. Most of these titles were included in Shaheen's writings, in particular Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Material in this series is not available for playback. Researchers may view an item's original container.
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 25)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 26)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 27)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 28)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 29)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 30)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 31)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 32)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 33)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 34)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 35)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 36)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 37)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 38)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 39)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 40)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 41)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 42)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 43)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 44)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 45)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 46)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 47)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 48)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 49)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 50)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 51)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 52)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 53)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 54)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 55)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 56)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 57)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 58)
  - Commercial video recordings, 1911-2012 (Box 59)
  - Commercial video recordings, 2004-2010 (Box 72, Dvd 1-4, Box Shared Tamiment 160)
  - Oldsmobile TV commercial with Arabs, 1980 (Box Shared Tamiment 012, 2 inch videoreel 535.0001)
  - Arabian Nights, undated (Box 71)
  - Aladdin's Lamp, undated (Box 71)
  - Somewhere in Egypt, undated (Box 71)
  - Trouble in Baghdad, undated (Box 71)
  - Beau Jest, undated (Box 71)
  - Tut Tut Magoo, undated (Box 71)
  - King Tut's Tomb, undated (Box 71)
  - Perils in a Harem, undated (Box 71)
  - Ali Baba and the Forty Thieves, undated (Box 71)
  - Foreign Legion, undated (Box 71)
  - Attack of the Moors, 1964; 2 Reels; 16mm film reel (Reel TAM_535_601, Reel TAM_535_602)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Handwritten note on canister reads "Vinegar Syndrome"
  - Tangier Incident, undated; 2 Reels; 16mm Film Reel (Reel TAM_535_603, Reel TAM_535_604)
  - Mozambique, undated; 3 Reels; 16mm film reels (Reel TAM_535_605, Reel TAM_535_606, Box Shared Tamiment 138)
  - Desert Hell, undated; 3 Reels; 16mm film reels (Reel TAM_535_607, Reel TAM_535_608, Box Shared Tamiment 138, Reel 3)